<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to Sir Peter Leicester's Addenda, or, Some things to be added in his Answer to Sir Thomas Mainwarings book written by the said Sir Thomas Mainwaring.</title>
            <author>Mainwaring, Thomas, Sir, 1623-1689.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70632</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M298</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18031</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11936398</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11936398</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51200</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70632)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51200)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 48:29 or 673:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to Sir Peter Leicester's Addenda, or, Some things to be added in his Answer to Sir Thomas Mainwarings book written by the said Sir Thomas Mainwaring.</title>
                  <author>Mainwaring, Thomas, Sir, 1623-1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 53 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Lowndes ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673/4 [i.e. 1674]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In respect to the alleged illegitimacy of Amicia Mainwaring, daughter of Hugh Cybeliok, Earl of Chester.</note>
                  <note>This item appears at reel 48:29 as Wing A3380 (number cancelled in Wing 2nd ed.), and at reel 673:9 as Wing (2nd ed.) M298.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mainwaring, Amicia.</term>
               <term>Leycester, Peter, --  Sir, 1614-1678. --  Historical antiquities.</term>
               <term>Mainwaring, Thomas, --  Sir, 1623-1689. --  Defence of Amicia, daughter of Hugh Cyveliok, Earl of Chester.</term>
               <term>Leycester, Peter, --  Sir, 1614-1678. --  Addenda, or, Some things to be added in my Answer to Sir Thomas Manwaring's book.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51200:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER TO Sir <hi>PETER LEICESTER'S</hi> Addenda, OR, Some things to be Added in his ANSWER to S<hi rend="sup">ir</hi> 
               <hi>THOMAS MAINWARINGS</hi> BOOK.</p>
            <p>WRITTEN By the ſaid Sir <hi>Thomas Mainwarings</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Lowndes</hi> over againſt <hi>Exeter-Houſe</hi> in the <hi>Strand,</hi> 1673/4.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:51200:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51200:2"/>
            <head>TO Sir <hi>Peter Leiceſter</hi> Baronet.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Received your <hi>Addenda</hi> to the <hi>Anſwer</hi> to my former Book, on Monday the 12th of <hi>January</hi> laſt; in writing of which, whether you are juſt to your word; or not, let the whole World Judge.</p>
            <p>As for that which you ſay in the firſt <hi>Page</hi> thereof, I think it was not worth your adding to what you had formerly written, unleſs you could make it to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that thoſe perſons whom you call judicious men, be ſuch whoſe opinions are like to be of equal weight with thoſe Judges and Heralds who are againſt you, which (I believe) will be very hard for you to do: And if you
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51200:3"/>could, we ſhould therein be but upon equal termes.</p>
            <p>When you tell me in your 2 <hi>Page,</hi> that you do give me two or three pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedents more, beſides that of <hi>Geva,</hi> to prove that Lands in thoſe elder ages did paſs <hi>in libero maritagio,</hi> I cannot but ſmile, to ſee that you ſtill ſay, that the gift to <hi>Geva</hi> was ſuch a Precedent, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering how in my <hi>Defence</hi> of <hi>Amicia, Page</hi> 43, 44. and ſo on to the middle of the 50 <hi>Page,</hi> as alſo, in my <hi>Reply</hi> to your <hi>Anſwer, p.</hi> 23. and <hi>p.</hi> 45, 46. and ſo on to the 60. <hi>Page,</hi> I have made it to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that it is very uncertain that the ſaid <hi>Geva</hi> was a Baſtard, but moſt certain that the Gift to <hi>Geva</hi> was not a Gift in <hi>Frank-marriage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I ſhall come to your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended new precedents, which you mention <hi>Page</hi> 2. and ſo on to the end of the 6 <hi>Page</hi> of your <hi>Addenda,</hi> and in my Anſwer thereto, I ſhall make it very clear that they are not ſuch precedents as you take them to be, but are groſs miſtakes of yours, you erring in no leſs then theſe five particulars following. Firſt, in conceiving that <hi>Joane</hi> wife of the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> and daughter to King
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51200:3"/>
               <hi>John,</hi> was that baſe daughter named <hi>Joane,</hi> which King <hi>John</hi> had by <hi>Agatha</hi> daughter to the ſecond <hi>William</hi> de <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rars</hi> Earl of <hi>Derby;</hi> Secondly, in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin</hi> did marry <hi>Joane</hi> daughter of King <hi>John</hi> in the year 1206. Thirdly, in alledging that King <hi>John</hi> gave <hi>Elleſmere in libero maritagio</hi> with his ſaid daughter <hi>Joane.</hi> Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in pretending that the Mannor of <hi>Budeford</hi> in <hi>Warwickſhire,</hi> and the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of <hi>Suttehall</hi> in <hi>Worceſterſhire</hi> were given by King <hi>John</hi> to the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin</hi> with any daughter of the ſaid King <hi>John.</hi> And laſtly, in ſaying that that <hi>Joane</hi> who was wife to <hi>Robert</hi> de <hi>Andeley,</hi> was the ſame <hi>Joane</hi> who was wife to the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt, you erre in ſaying that <hi>Joane</hi> who was the wife of the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> was the ſame <hi>Joane</hi> which King <hi>John</hi> had by the ſaid <hi>Agatha;</hi> For as you may ſee in your <hi>Hiſtorical Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, p.</hi> 132. compared with <hi>Vincent, p.</hi> 204. (which is the place you bring for proof of what you ſay) the ſaid <hi>Agatha</hi> was daughter to <hi>William Ferrars</hi> Earl of <hi>Derby,</hi> by his wife <hi>Agnes</hi> the third ſiſter and coheir of <hi>Randle Blundevil</hi> Earl of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51200:4"/>
               <hi>Cheſter</hi> and <hi>Lincolne,</hi> which <hi>Agnes</hi> was daughter of <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> Earl of <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> by his wife <hi>Bertred.</hi> Now the ſaid <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> dying as appears in your <hi>Hiſt. Ant. p.</hi> 134. in the year 1181. and the ſaid <hi>Bertred</hi> his wife (as is proved <hi>Rot. de Dominabus pueris,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in Scacc. penes Remem. R. ſub Tit. Linc. Rot.</hi> 1.) being but Twenty four years of age when her ſaid husband dyed, it will from thence appear, that <hi>Joane</hi> daughter of the ſaid <hi>Agatha</hi> could not poſſibly be the wife of the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin;</hi> For, if we ſuppoſe that <hi>Randle Blundevil</hi> was younger then his third ſiſter <hi>Agnes</hi> (which I am confident you do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve) and that the ſaid <hi>Bertred</hi> was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten with Child at thirteen yeares of age, and came ſo nimbly with her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren as to have her firſt daughter when ſhe was fourteen years old, her ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond daughter when ſhe was fifteen years old, and her third daughter <hi>Agnes</hi> when ſhe the ſaid <hi>Bertred</hi> was ſixteen years old, then the ſaid <hi>Agnes</hi> would be eight years of age in the ſaid year 1181. If we alſo ſuppoſe the ſaid <hi>Agatha</hi> to be the eldeſt of the ſix children of the ſaid <hi>William Ferrars</hi> and <hi>Agnes,</hi> (though ſhe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51200:4"/>might be the youngeſt) and that ſhe the ſaid <hi>Agnes</hi> had the ſaid <hi>Agatha</hi> when ſhe the ſaid <hi>Agnes</hi> was but fourteen years old, then ſhe the ſaid <hi>Agatha</hi> would be born in the year 1187. If we alſo ſuppoſe that the ſaid <hi>Agatha</hi> had her daughter <hi>Joane</hi> when ſhe the ſaid <hi>Agatha</hi> was but fourteen years old, then the ſaid <hi>Joane</hi> would be born in the year 1021. and yet by all this ſtrange way of reckoning, <hi>Joane</hi> the daughter of <hi>Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha</hi> would have been but about three years of age, when the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin</hi> was married, which (as anon will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear) was in the year 1204. So that this <hi>Joane</hi> daughter of <hi>Agatha</hi> was ſo far from being wife to the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> that there is no likelihood that ſhe was born at the time of the ſaid <hi>Lhewellins</hi> marriage. But the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin</hi> was 28 years of age in the year 1204, For, <hi>Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſter Giraldus Cambrenſis</hi> in his <hi>Itiner. Cambr.</hi> printed at <hi>London</hi> 1585. <hi>p.</hi> 64. and 203. tells us, that in the year 1188, (at which time the ſaid <hi>Silveſter</hi> was li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving) the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin</hi> was 12 years old.</p>
            <p>Secondly, you run in to another erro in alledging that the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:51200:5"/>did marry his wife <hi>Joan</hi> in the year 1206. whereas he was her Husband in the year 1204. in the 6 year of King <hi>John,</hi> as will appear by your own Authors, <hi>Stow</hi> and <hi>Speed,</hi> and by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral others; as alſo by this Copy of King <hi>John</hi>'s Precept to the Sheriff of <hi>Shropſhire,</hi> to make Livery of the ſaid Lordſhip of <hi>Elleſmere.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ex Rot. Clauſo de anno Sexto Regis</hi> Johannis (<hi>in arce</hi> Lond.) <hi>membra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rex Vicecom. Salop. Salutem. Scias quod dedimus dilecto filio noſtro</hi> Lewelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no <hi>manerium de</hi> Ellesmere, <hi>cum omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus pertinentiis ſuis, in maritagio filiae no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrae, Et ideo, &amp;c. Teſte, &amp;c, apud Wigorn.</hi> 23. <hi>Martii.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Thirdly, You are guilty of a third error, in pretending that King <hi>John</hi> did give the Lordſhip of <hi>Elleſmere, in libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro maritagio</hi> with his Daughter <hi>Joan;</hi> for your own Authors, as well as the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Record, do only ſay, that it was given <hi>in Maritagio;</hi> ſo that your argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Elleſmere</hi> was given <hi>in mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagio,</hi> and therefore was given <hi>in libero
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51200:5"/>maritagio,</hi> is very irrational; For I have ſhewed in the 39 and 40 pages of my <hi>Reply</hi> to your <hi>Anſwer,</hi> that <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritagium</hi> is twofold, and that Lands may be given <hi>in maritagio,</hi> to one that is not of the Blood, but (as I have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten proved) Lands cannot be given <hi>in free-marriage,</hi> but with one that is of the whole Blood, neither can they be ſo given, unleſs the word <hi>liberum</hi> be uſed as well as the word <hi>maritagium,</hi> as I have ſhewed in the 56 and 57 pages of my ſaid <hi>Reply.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if it were ſo, that you could have proved <hi>Joan,</hi> the wife of the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> to have been the baſe Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of King <hi>John</hi> by the ſaid <hi>Agatha:</hi> and if it had been ſo, that this gift of <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſmere</hi> had been <hi>in libero maritagio,</hi> yet it would have ſtood you in no ſtead; for as you may ſee <hi>Coke</hi> upon <hi>Littleton, fol.</hi> 21. <hi>b. if the Donee</hi> (in a Gift of Frank-marriage) <hi>that is cauſe of the gift be not of the blood of the Donor,</hi> yet there may paſs an Eſtate for life, if Livery be made; And in this caſe of <hi>Elleſmere</hi> (as appears before) Livery was made; And you may find in the <hi>Welſh Hiſtory,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:51200:6"/>put out by Doctor <hi>Powell,</hi> p. 306. and <hi>Mat. Par.</hi> p. 625, and 626. that though <hi>Elleſmere</hi> was injoyed by the ſaid <hi>Lhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wellin,</hi> yet it was not long enjoyed by his Son <hi>David,</hi> but was the next year after the death of <hi>Lhewellin</hi> in (or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout) the Feaſt of the Decollation of <hi>St. John Baptiſt,</hi> in the hands of King <hi>Henry</hi> the III. and as appears by good Record, the cuſtody thereof, together with the Hundred of <hi>Elleſmere,</hi> was afterwards committed by the ſame King to the Truſt of <hi>Hamonle Strange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly you are alſo miſtaken in thinking that the Mannors of <hi>Budeford</hi> and <hi>Suttehall,</hi> were given by King <hi>John</hi> to <hi>Lhewellin</hi> with his Daughter <hi>Joan,</hi> and for all your boaſting demand of what can be clearer? yet your Deed is far from proving what you ſuppoſe it doth; For it neither ſays that King <hi>John</hi> gave thoſe Mannors <hi>cum filia ſua baſtarda,</hi> or that he gave them <hi>cum filia ſua.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay in the fourth page of your <hi>Addenda,</hi> that <hi>the ſaid Prince</hi> Lhewellin <hi>never married any
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51200:6"/>Daughter of King</hi> John <hi>but the ſaid</hi> Joan, I ſhall thus far agree with you, That he married a Daughter of King <hi>John</hi>'s, named <hi>Joan;</hi> and but one Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his, but not that <hi>Joan</hi> which you ſuppoſe. But certainly your conceit that <hi>Lhewellin</hi> could not have a former Wife, unleſs ſhe was another Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the ſaid K. <hi>John,</hi> is a very wild one; For, King <hi>John</hi> might give thoſe Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors to <hi>Lhewellin</hi> with any Woman that was of his kindred; and it is very apparent that our Engliſh Kings about that time were very deſirous to have Alliance with the Princes of <hi>North-Wales;</hi> For, beſides that Match of <hi>Lhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wellin</hi> with the Daughter of King <hi>John,</hi> and this Match of <hi>John Scot</hi> with <hi>Hellen,</hi> Daughter of the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin, David ap Owen</hi> (Uncle to the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin</hi>) did marry a Siſter of King <hi>Henry</hi> the II. as you may ſee in <hi>Sylveſter Giraldus.</hi> p. 203. and the <hi>Welſh Hiſtory,</hi> p. 235. And King <hi>Edward</hi> the I. alſo cauſed <hi>Lhewel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin ap Griffith Lhewellin,</hi> to marry a Daughter of <hi>Simon de Mountford,</hi> Earl of <hi>Lieceſter,</hi> which Daughter the ſaid Earl had by a Daughter of King <hi>John,</hi> and this, although the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin, ap
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51200:7"/>Griffith Lhewellin</hi> would have married elſewhere, as you may read in <hi>Knighton col.</hi> 2462. <hi>num.</hi> 26, and <hi>num.</hi> 50. And although we cannot tell the name of her who was the firſt wife of that <hi>Lhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wellin,</hi> who married <hi>Joan</hi> the Daughter of King <hi>John</hi> as aforeſaid, we being ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of that, as we alſo are of the Wives of many great perſons, and of many other things in thoſe elder ages, yet the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin</hi> muſt neceſſarily have a former Wife, as will appear by theſe following Reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe moſt Writers, as <hi>Fabian</hi> in the 7 Part of his <hi>Chronicle,</hi> p. 13. a. <hi>Stow,</hi> p. 167. a. Doctor <hi>Powell</hi> in his Notes on the <hi>Welſh Hiſtory,</hi> p, 259. <hi>York,</hi> p. 20. <hi>Speed</hi> in his <hi>Hiſtory</hi> printed at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> 1632. p. 573. <hi>Vincent</hi> on <hi>Brooke,</hi> p. 204. <hi>Cambden</hi> in his <hi>Britania,</hi> in Latine, Printed at <hi>London,</hi> 1607. p. 453. and <hi>Knighton,</hi> col, 2417. num. 42. do all tell us of Lands given by the ſaid King <hi>John</hi> to the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> with his Daughter <hi>Joan,</hi> and yet none of them do ſay, that theſe Mannors of <hi>Budeford</hi> and <hi>Suttehall,</hi> or either of them were given with the ſaid <hi>Joan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:51200:7"/>Secondly, Becauſe our beſt Authors, who tell us what Children the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin</hi> had by the ſaid <hi>Joane,</hi> do only name one ſon, viz. <hi>David,</hi> and two daughters, viz. <hi>Marret</hi> married to <hi>John</hi> de <hi>Bruſe,</hi> and <hi>Gladys</hi> married to Sir <hi>Baph Mortimer,</hi> but none of them doth name <hi>Hellen,</hi> ſo that it ſeems <hi>Hellen</hi> was no daughter of his by the ſaid <hi>Joane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Becauſe (as before appears) the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin</hi> married the ſaid <hi>Joane</hi> in the year 1204. Now <hi>Randle</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi> coming to the City <hi>Damiata</hi> in the beginning of the year 1218. as you may ſee in <hi>Matt. Paris, p.</hi> 303. <hi>n.</hi> 24. &amp; 309. <hi>n.</hi> 16. compared together, and this Match of <hi>John Scot</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Hellen</hi> as you may find in <hi>Knighton, col.</hi> 2430. <hi>n.</hi> 9. being agreed on by <hi>Randle</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſaid <hi>Randle</hi> went thither (and by conſequence about the year 1217.) What likelihood is there that the ſaid <hi>Joane</hi> could have any daughter old enough to be married to the ſaid <hi>John Scot,</hi> it being impoſſible that <hi>Lhewellin</hi> could at that time have any Child by King <hi>John</hi>'s daughter, who could be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51200:8"/>above the age of twelve years; And though you pretend that <hi>John Scot</hi> did marry the ſaid <hi>Hellen</hi> about the year 1222, yet you do that, becauſe ſhe could not well be marriageable till about that time if her Mother had been married in that year, which you faſly ſuppoſed ſhe was. But there is no likelihood that <hi>Randle Blundevil</hi> would go to the <hi>Holy Land</hi> after the ſaid marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age was agreed on, before it was Conſummated, and that he had thereby ſome aſſurance that the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin</hi> would keep that peace which was then made: But, <hi>Lhewellen</hi> might very well have a daughter by a former wife, who in the year 1217. might be old enough to be married to <hi>John Scot,</hi> for the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin</hi> (as appears by the proofes before) was then aged 41 years; And it is like that <hi>John Scot</hi> was then of a good age, for, if his Grandmother <hi>Bertred</hi> had his Mother <hi>Maude</hi> when ſhe the ſaid <hi>Bertred</hi> was 18 years of age, and if his Mother <hi>Maude</hi> had him the ſaid <hi>John Scot</hi> when ſhe was alſo 18 years of age, yet <hi>John Scot</hi> would be born in the year 1193, and would be 24 years old in the year 1217.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:51200:8"/>Fourthly, (which doth abſolutely clear the point) the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin</hi> could not poſſibly have given the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors aforeſaid <hi>in free marriage</hi> with his daughter <hi>Hellen</hi> unto the ſaid <hi>John Scot,</hi> unleſs they had been given to the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin</hi> with a former wife, and that the ſaid <hi>Hellen</hi> was the heir unto his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer wife; For when lands are given <hi>in free marriage,</hi> the husband hath not the inheritance of the ſaid lands, neither hath he ſo much as an eſtate for life, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til he be Tenant by the Curteſie of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> And you cannot pretend (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your old ſubterfuge) that the Law in this point was differently holden in thoſe elder times from what it is now; For, as you may ſee in my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> on <hi>Littleton, fol.</hi> 22. <hi>a.</hi> the husband in the time of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, was ſo far from having the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of Lands given to him in Frankmarriage, that if he and his wife were divorced, the woman ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the whole land; And for this he cites in the Margent 13 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>tit. Aſs.</hi> 19 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>Aſs.</hi> 83. with ſeveral other proofes of the like nature; Alſo in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51200:9"/>time of King <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. as you may ſee in the Antient Treatiſe called <hi>Fleta,</hi> the inheritance in theſe caſes was in the wife, and not in the husband: For in the 3 Book and 11th Chapter, <hi>de dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus in maritagiis</hi> it is thus ſaid, <hi>Et quamvis fiat mentio in donatione, quod terra data ſit in maritagium tali viro, cum tali uxore, res data tamen eſt liberum tenementum uxoris, &amp; non viri, cum non habeat niſi cuſtodiam cum uxore, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nec liberum tenementum ſibi accreſcat, per legem Angliae: Secus ſi pro homagio &amp; ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitio viri &amp; in Maritagium facta fuerit donatio.</hi> And ſo alſo <hi>Bracton</hi> (who lived in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, and alſo in the time of the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin</hi>) <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. ſays, <hi>Si au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem fiat mentio quod terra data ſit in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritagium cum uxore &amp; eorum haeredibus, communes haeredes de corpore utriuſque admittantur, qui ſi defecerint, revertitur terra data, &amp; alii remotiores excludun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: quia res data eſt liberum tenemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum uxoris, &amp; non viri, cum non habeat</hi> niſi cuſtodiam <hi>cum uxore. Si autem ſic terra detur in Maritagium, viro cum uxore &amp; eorum haeredibus, pro homagio &amp; ſervitio viri (quod fit aliquando) licet
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51200:9"/>detur in liberum maritagium, quae ſunt ſibi ad invicem adverſantia ſive repugnantia, tunc prefertur homagium, &amp; erit acſifieret donatio tam viro quam uxori.</hi> And ſo alſo my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> on <hi>Littleton, fol.</hi> 21. <hi>b.</hi> tells us, <hi>That if the King give Land to a man with a woman of his kindred in frank-marriage, and the woman dyeth without iſſue, the Man in the Kings caſe ſhall not hold it for his life, becauſe the woman was the cauſe of the gift, but otherwayes it is in the caſe of a common perſon,</hi> and for this in the Margent he cites 9 <hi>H.</hi> 3. <hi>Dower.</hi> 202. So alſo Mr. <hi>Glanvile</hi> (who l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ved in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and before the time of the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin</hi>) <hi>lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 18. to the ſame purpoſe ſayes, <hi>Cum quis itaque terram aliquam cum uxore ſua in maritagium ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perit, ſi ex eadem uxore ſua haeredem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buerit filium, vel filiam clamantem &amp; auditum infra quatuor parietes ſi idem vir uxorem ſuam ſupervixerit, ſive vixerit haeres ſive non, illi in vita ſua remanet maritagium illud, poſt mortem vero ipſius ad donatorem vel ejus haeredes eſt reverſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. Sin autem ex uxore ſuae nunquam habuerit haeredem, tunc ſtatim poſt mortem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xeris ad donatorem vel haeredes ejus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertetur
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51200:10"/>maritagium;</hi> ſo that it is clear that the lands which were given with the ſaid <hi>Hellen</hi> to the ſaid <hi>John Scot</hi> were given to the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin</hi> with a former wife, who was Kinſwoman to the ſaid King <hi>John,</hi> and Mother to the ſaid <hi>Hellen,</hi> for otherwiſe the ſaid Gift to <hi>John Scot</hi> could not be good; But if they were given to the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin</hi> with a wife who was Mother to the ſaid <hi>Hellen,</hi> but dead at the time of the gift to the ſaid <hi>John Scot,</hi> then the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin</hi> being Tenant by the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie of <hi>England,</hi> and the inheritance being in the ſaid <hi>Hellen</hi> he might paſs away his Eſtate to the ſaid <hi>John Scot</hi> with the ſaid <hi>Hellen,</hi> and they might lawfully hold the ſaid Mannors <hi>in libero maritagio,</hi> according to the Agreement made betwixt the ſaid <hi>Randle</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi> and <hi>Lincolne,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Lhewel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi> Prince of <hi>North-Wales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, You erre a fifth time in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that <hi>Joane</hi> the wife of <hi>Robert</hi> de <hi>Audeley</hi> was the ſame <hi>Joane</hi> who was wife to the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin;</hi> For, that cannot poſſibly be, becauſe <hi>Robert</hi> de <hi>Audeley</hi> married <hi>Joane</hi> the baſe daughter of King <hi>John</hi> by <hi>Agatha,</hi> who might well be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riageable in the 14 year of King <hi>Henry</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:51200:10"/>the Third, which fell out to be in the years 1229. and 1230. But, I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhewed that there is no poſſibility that the ſaid <hi>Joane</hi> daughter of <hi>Agatha</hi> could be wife to <hi>Lhewellin</hi> in the year 1204. nor any likelihood that ſhe then was born. And this miſtake of yours doth further appear, becauſe (as before is ſhewed) Prince <hi>Lhewellin</hi> was husband to the ſaid <hi>Joane</hi> in the year 1204. and (as you well know and confeſs) he dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not till the 24th year of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 3d. How then can that <hi>Ioane</hi> who was wife to <hi>Robert</hi> de <hi>Audeley</hi> in the 14th year of King <hi>H.</hi> 3. be the ſame <hi>Joane</hi> who was wife to <hi>Lhewellin?</hi> unleſs ſhe had two husbands living at one time. Or, How can what your Author <hi>Vincent</hi> ſayes be true, <hi>That ſhe was re-married to</hi> Robert <hi>de</hi> Audley, 14 H. 3. <hi>after the death of</hi> Lhewellin, ſeeing the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin</hi> died not till the 24th year of <hi>Henry</hi> 3d? and did alſo outlive his wife <hi>Joane</hi> three yeares? Certainly, if <hi>Vincent</hi> had known as well as you, how long the ſaid <hi>Lhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ellin</hi> lived, he would never have ſaid that <hi>Joane</hi> the wife of <hi>Robert</hi> de <hi>Audley</hi> was the ſame <hi>Joane</hi> who was wife of <hi>Lhewellin;</hi> But though you do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51200:11"/>that <hi>Vincent</hi> did erre in ſaying <hi>Lhewellin</hi> was dead, when <hi>Joane</hi> was mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to <hi>Robert</hi> de <hi>Audeley,</hi> yet you would willingly juſtifie the other part of his error, in making <hi>Audeleys</hi> wife <hi>Joane</hi> to be the ſame woman with <hi>Lhewellins</hi> wife <hi>Joane,</hi> and to do this, you fancy that <hi>Lhewellin</hi> was divorced from his wife <hi>Joane,</hi> though there be no Author who doth alleadge any ſuch thing. And, Can we think that a Prince of <hi>North-Wales,</hi> and a daughter of <hi>King John</hi> could be divorced, and one or both of them marry again in the life-time of each other, and no writer take notice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of? Or, can it be, that <hi>Mat. Paris,</hi> who lived at that very time, ſhould (in his 365. <hi>Page</hi>) ſpeak of <hi>William</hi> de <hi>Braus</hi> his being taken in Adultery with the ſaid <hi>Joane,</hi> with an <hi>(ut dicebatur)</hi> only? Or, the <hi>Welch Hiſtory</hi> (<hi>p.</hi> 286.) with an <hi>(as it was reported)</hi> if the Adultery was ſo notorious, as that ſhe was divor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced for it? Indeed, you tell us out of <hi>Knighton, col.</hi> 2439. that <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1228. 13 <hi>H.</hi> 3. Leolinus <hi>Princeps Walliae rebllare cepit:—Tandem vero poſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſus varios, &amp; diſcrimina multa, per quoddam maritagium cum Rege concorda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51200:11"/>eſt, &amp; in pace dimiſsus;</hi> and from theſe words, <hi>per quoddam maritagium,</hi> you would inſinuate a <hi>Divorce,</hi> and a new Marriage of the ſaid <hi>Joane,</hi> with <hi>Robert</hi> de <hi>Audeley,</hi> which divorce and marriage is further fetcht then any thing that I ever heard of in all my life; For, it is not likely that the puting away of the Kings Siſter could be a means to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure Peace, and none knowes betwixt what parties the marriage there ſpoken of was; But you did well to break off at the words <hi>in pace dimiſſus,</hi> for if you had added theſe words of <hi>Knighton,</hi> which immediately follow the other, viz. <hi>Anno Domini ſequenti</hi> (the Figures 1229. being alſo put in the margent) Lewelinus <hi>eundem</hi> Willielmum <hi>de</hi> Braus <hi>Baronem nobilem quem ad feſta Paſchalia invitaverat, poſt epularum copiam ſuper adulterio &amp; violatione uxoris ſuae accuſans, &amp; malitioſe eum &amp; hoſtiliter ingreſſus eſt, &amp; eum in carcerem trudens morte turpiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma &amp; abſque omni judicio ſententialiter interemit.</hi> It would from thence have appeared that neither the Divorce or ſecond marriage of the ſaid <hi>Joane</hi> could thereby be meant, unleſs you would have a Divorce in the year 1228, for an
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51200:12"/>Adultery not committed till the year 1229. And with <hi>Knighton</hi> agrees the ſaid <hi>Mat. Maris, p.</hi> 365. <hi>n.</hi> 10. (menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in the 5 <hi>Page</hi> of your <hi>Addenda</hi>) who ſaith, that William <hi>de</hi> Braus <hi>was hanged for that ſuppoſed Adultery, in the moneth of April, in the year</hi> 1230. And we well know, there is but one week betwixt the laſt day of the year 1229. and the firſt day of <hi>April</hi> 1230.</p>
            <p>Alſo, in the 6 <hi>Page</hi> of your <hi>Addenda,</hi> where you tell us out of the <hi>Welſh Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory</hi> put out by Doctor Powel, <hi>that</hi> Lew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ellin's <hi>wife died in the year</hi> 1237. if you would have added what is further ſaid in the ſame Page, it would have given ſatisfaction that <hi>Lhewellins wife was never divorced,</hi> For, <hi>Page</hi> 293. you may thus read, <hi>The next Spring</hi> (1237.) <hi>died</hi> Joane <hi>daughter to King</hi> John, <hi>Princeſs of</hi> Wales, <hi>and was buried upon the Sea ſhore within the Iſle of</hi> Angleſey <hi>at</hi> Lhanvaes <hi>as her pleaſure was, where the Prince did build an houſe of barefoot-Friars over her grave.</hi> Now certainly the <hi>Welſh History</hi> would not then have called her <hi>Princeſs of Wales,</hi> nor her husband have built that houſe over her, if ſhe had been di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorced
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51200:12"/>from <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> and Married to the ſaid <hi>Robert</hi> de <hi>Audeley.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any object, That though <hi>Joane</hi> the wife of <hi>Lhewellin</hi> was not the baſe daughter of King <hi>John</hi> by <hi>Agatha,</hi> yet it is like ſhe was his baſe daughter by ſome other woman, becauſe of thoſe Authors which you cite to that purpoſe; I anſwer, and ſay, that it is nothing to the caſe of <hi>Amicia,</hi> whether the ſaid <hi>Joane</hi> was a Baſtard or not, as I have before proved; But however it doth not yet certainly appear to me that ſhe was ſo; For, though <hi>Vincent</hi> upon <hi>Brooke, Speed, Stow,</hi> and the Monke of <hi>Cheſter</hi> who did write the <hi>Poly-Chronicon,</hi> and ſome others do ſay, that ſhe was a Baſtard, yet they are not much to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, becauſe the ſaid Author of the <hi>Poly-Chronicon,</hi> (as <hi>Voſſius</hi> tells you in his Book <hi>de Hiſtoricis Latinis, p.</hi> 487.) dyed in the year 1363. which was 159. years after <hi>Lhewellin</hi> married the ſaid <hi>Ioane,</hi> and yet the ſaid Monke lived long before any other Author (which I have taken notice of) who doth call her a Baſtard. Let us therefore examine the matter a little; and in order thereto, let
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51200:13"/>us obſerve how many wives the ſaid King <hi>Iohn</hi> had.</p>
            <p>Firſt, he married <hi>Alais</hi> daughter of the Earl of <hi>Moriana</hi> in the year 1173. as you may read in <hi>Brompton</hi>'s <hi>Chronicon, col.</hi> 1082. <hi>n.</hi> 35. <hi>Hoveden</hi> (<hi>Frankfurt</hi> Edition, printed 1601.) <hi>Page</hi> 532. <hi>n.</hi> 5. <hi>Matt. Paris</hi> (put out by Doctor <hi>Watts</hi>) <hi>Page</hi> 127. <hi>n.</hi> 5. (which Editions of <hi>Hove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> and <hi>Paris,</hi> I do all along follow) and the like you may find in <hi>Vincent</hi> upon <hi>Brooke, Page</hi> 133. who alſo there tells you, that by <hi>Moriana</hi> is not meant <hi>More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> but <hi>Savoy,</hi> with which <hi>Matt. Par. p.</hi> 751. <hi>n.</hi> 46. doth alſo accord; But the ſaid <hi>Alais</hi> being then ſcarcely ſeven yeares of age, as you may ſee in <hi>Matt. Paris, p.</hi> 127. <hi>n.</hi> 6. and dying preſently after, the ſaid King <hi>Iohn</hi> could not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly have any iſſue by that wife.</p>
            <p>Soon after this, <hi>viz.</hi> in the year 1176. (as you may read in <hi>Hoveden, p.</hi> 553. <hi>n.</hi> 46. and <hi>Matt. Paris, p.</hi> 132. <hi>n.</hi> 29) there was an Agreement for a marriage to be had between the ſaid <hi>Iohn</hi> (then youngeſt ſon of the ſaid King <hi>H.</hi> 2.) and a daughter of <hi>William</hi> Earl of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:51200:13"/>ſon of <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> which ſaid daughter is not there named, but her name was <hi>Hawiſia</hi> or <hi>Avis,</hi> and the marriage afterwards took effect, but he was divorced from her in the year 1200, as will anon appear.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, immediately upon his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce he married <hi>Iſabel</hi> daughter of the Earl of <hi>Engoliſme,</hi> who was his laſt wife; for, ſhe ſurvived him; and by her he had iſſue (as will be agreed by all) <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> (afterwards King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third) <hi>Richard,</hi> Earl of <hi>Cornwall,</hi> (afterwards King of the <hi>Romanes</hi>) <hi>Ioane</hi> wife of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> the ſecond, King of <hi>Scots, Elea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,</hi> firſt married to <hi>William Marſhal</hi> the younger, Earl of <hi>Pembroke,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to <hi>Simon Mountford</hi> Earl of <hi>Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter,</hi> as alſo <hi>Iſabel,</hi> who was ſixth wife to <hi>Frederick</hi> the ſecond, Emperour of <hi>Germany.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But King <hi>Iohn</hi> marrying the ſaid <hi>Iſabel</hi> in the year 1200. could have no child by her old enough to be married to the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin</hi> in the year 1204.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:51200:14"/>Neither could <hi>Ioane</hi> the wife of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> King of <hi>Scots</hi> be the ſame <hi>Ioane</hi> who was wife to <hi>Robert</hi> de <hi>Audeley,</hi> for, ſhe was wife to the ſaid <hi>Alexander</hi> in the year 1221. as appears in your <hi>Hiſt. Ant. p.</hi> 60. and <hi>Mat. Paris, p.</hi> 313. <hi>n.</hi> 12. and died before her husband (ſay you) in the year 1236. and was buried at <hi>London;</hi> But, <hi>Mat. Paris,</hi> who lived in the ſame time with her (<hi>p.</hi> 468. <hi>n.</hi> 34.) tells you the very day of her death, and ſays ſhe died in the year 1238. in <hi>England,</hi> and was buried at <hi>Tarente.</hi> But you in your 60<hi>p.</hi> and <hi>Mat. Paris, p.</hi> 770. <hi>n.</hi> 39. do agree that the ſaid <hi>Alexander</hi> did ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive the ſaid <hi>Ioane,</hi> and that he died in the year 1249.</p>
            <p>The only queſtion then will be, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Lhewellins</hi> wife was King <hi>Iohns</hi> legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate daughter by his wife Hawiſia? which if ſhe was, then ſome of our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors taking notice but of two daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters named <hi>Ioane,</hi> which the ſaid King had, did thereupon miſtake <hi>Ioane</hi> the wife of <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> for <hi>Ioane</hi> the wife of <hi>Robert</hi> de <hi>Audeley,</hi> and ſo did miſlead ſeveral of our later Authors into the like error.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:51200:14"/>Sure I am, that <hi>Mat. Paris,</hi> who was contemporary with the ſaid <hi>Ioane, p.</hi> 231. <hi>n.</hi> 52. calls her <hi>the Kings daughter,</hi> without the addition of Baſtard, or any thing tending thereto; His words are theſe, <hi>Quo facto, venit alius Nuncius ex parte filiae ejuſdem Regis uxoris videlicet</hi> Leolini <hi>Regis</hi> Walliae, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Alſo in the raign of King <hi>H.</hi> 3. her ſon <hi>David</hi> is by him (<hi>p.</hi> 537. 569. and in many other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) ſtiled <hi>Nepos Regis,</hi> and <hi>p.</hi> 695. called <hi>Nepos Regis ex Sorore,</hi> and <hi>p.</hi> 570. he is ſaid to be <hi>propinquus Regi conſanguinita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te.</hi> Alſo <hi>Knighton, col.</hi> 2417. <hi>n.</hi> 42. thus ſays of her, <hi>Rex Johannes dedit fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ſuam Leolino Principi Walliae in uxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem, &amp; cum ea dedit caſtellum &amp; totum territorium de</hi> Elleſmere <hi>in confinio</hi> Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liae. And the King himſelf in the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <hi>Record</hi> gives her the title of <hi>filiae noſtrae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo in <hi>Lib. Barlings</hi> (in which Book beſides what concernes the Abby of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings</hi> in <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> there are certain <hi>Annals</hi> (beginning <hi>An.</hi> 1050. and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>An.</hi> 1231.) ſhe is called the ſaid
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51200:15"/>Kings daughter, without the Addition of Baſtard; For, as I am informed by a judicious perſon, who, at my requeſt did lately ſearch the ſaid Book in Sir <hi>Iohn Cottons</hi> Library, theſe words <hi>Lewelinus diſponſavit filiam Regis</hi> I. are the only words, <hi>fol.</hi> 22. <hi>b.</hi> which concern the ſaid matter: And yet you, in the 2d. <hi>Page</hi> of your <hi>Addenda</hi> do ſay, <hi>That the ſaid</hi> Joane Lib. Barlings, Fol. 22. <hi>b. is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged and called baſe daughter of K.</hi> John. I hope therefore the Reader will take heed how farr he gives credit to what you ſay.</p>
            <p>Neither have I as yet found any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor who lived in that Age with her, who hath ſaid that ſhe was a Baſtard; Indeed, our later Authors as <hi>Vincent</hi> and others, who ſay that ſhe was illegiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, do many of them ſay, That King <hi>Iohn</hi> was divorced from his ſecond wife, as well for that ſhe was barren, as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the degrees of conſanguinity, which barrenneſs, if it could be made to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, would certainly prove the ſaid <hi>Ioane</hi> to be a Baſtard; And, this opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath ſo far prevailed in this laſt age, that whereas learned Mr. <hi>Cambden,</hi> as
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51200:15"/>you may ſee in his <hi>Britannia</hi> in Latine printed at <hi>London</hi> 1607. <hi>p.</hi> 259. ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Divorce of the ſaid <hi>Hawiſia</hi> (whoſe name he miſtakes and calls <hi>Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel</hi>) doth only uſe theſe words <hi>illam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudiatam,</hi> Doctor <hi>Philemon Holland</hi> in the Engliſh Tranſlation (unjuſtly) ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it thus, <hi>That King</hi> John <hi>did repudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate her upon pretences, as well that ſhe was barren, as that they were within the prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited degrees of conſanguinity.</hi> But our antient Hiſtorians ſay nothing of her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Barren.</p>
            <p>For this ſee <hi>Hoveden</hi> (who was living all the time that <hi>Hawiſia</hi> was wife to <hi>K.</hi> John) <hi>p.</hi> 803. <hi>n.</hi> 34. in the year 1200. <hi>Eodem Anno factum eſt divortium inter</hi> Johannem <hi>regem Angliae et</hi> Hawiſam <hi>uxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem ejus filiam</hi> Willielmi <hi>comitis</hi> Glouce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrriae <hi>per</hi> Heliam Burdegalenſem <hi>Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>epiſcopum, &amp; per</hi> Willielmum <hi>Pictaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſem, &amp; per</hi> Henricum <hi>Sanctonenſem epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copos: erant enim affines in tertio gradu conſanguinitatis. Facto ita<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Divortio inter</hi> Johannem <hi>regent Angliae, &amp; uxorent ſuam, ipſe Rex Angliae conſilio domini ſui</hi> Philippi <hi>regis</hi> Franciae <hi>duxit ſibi in uxorem</hi> Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:51200:16"/>
               <hi>filiam</hi> Ailmari <hi>comitis de</hi> Engoliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So alſo <hi>Mat. Paris</hi> (living in the time of the ſaid <hi>Ioane</hi>) <hi>p.</hi> 200. <hi>n.</hi> 23. in the ſaid year 1200. <hi>Eodem tempore celebrato Divortio inter Regem</hi> Anglorum <hi>&amp; uxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orem ſuam</hi> Hawiſam <hi>comitis</hi> Gloverniae <hi>filiam, eo quod affines erant in tertio gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du conſanguinitis. Duxit idem Rex, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilio Regis</hi> Francorum Iſabel <hi>filiam comitis</hi> Engoliſmi.</p>
            <p>So alſo <hi>Mat. Weſtminſter</hi> in that Editi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on printed at <hi>London,</hi> 1570. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 76. <hi>n.</hi> 25. <hi>Anno gratiae. M. CC. Rex</hi> Johan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Iſabellam <hi>filiam comitis</hi> Engoliſmi <hi>duxit in uxorem &amp; Dominica proxima an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te feſtum ſancti</hi> Dyoniſii <hi>conſecrata eſt in reginam ab</hi> Huberto <hi>Cantuarienſi</hi> Archie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopo, <hi>quia celebratum fuit divortium inter ipſum &amp;</hi> Hawiſiam <hi>comitis</hi> Glover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae <hi>filiam, eo quod contingebant ſe in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio conſanguinitatis gradu.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now certainly theſe antient Authors muſt needs in this point be credited be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe that lived ſo long after them, and eſpecially ſince all thoſe that I have
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51200:16"/>met with who ſay ſhe was barren, or do call her a Baſtard, do not one of them know her true Chriſtian-name, but are either ſilent therein, or elſe (which the moſt of them do) do call her <hi>Iſabel</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>Hawiſia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See alſo the words of <hi>Rad.</hi> de <hi>Diceto</hi> (who lived in the time of the ſaid King <hi>Iohn</hi>) <hi>col.</hi> 706. <hi>n.</hi> 5. which words are theſe, <hi>Celebratum eſt divortium inter</hi> Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannem <hi>regem Angliae &amp; filiam comitis</hi> Gloceſtriae <hi>in</hi> Normannia, <hi>ab epiſcopis</hi> Liſorienſi, Baiocenſi, Abrincenſi. <hi>&amp; aliis epiſcopis qui interfuerant, quam ipſe tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore patris permiſſione</hi> Romanae <hi>eccleſiae duxerat in uxorem cum Comitatibus de</hi> Gloceſtria, <hi>de</hi> Sumerſatum, <hi>de</hi> Devene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, <hi>de</hi> Cornwaille, <hi>et aliis quamplurimis per</hi> Angliam <hi>honoribus. Set ille ſublimio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris thori ſpe raptatus, conſilio pravorum cam abegit, unde magnam ſummi Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis ſcilicet,</hi> Innocentii tertii, <hi>et totius curiae</hi> Romanae <hi>indignationem incurrit, praeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens temere contra leges et canones diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere quod eorum fuerat auctoritate colliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:51200:17"/>And now let any man judge, if ſhe had been barren, whether that would not have been alleadged as a cauſe of King <hi>Iohns</hi> putting her away, as well as his deſire of matching into a more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime family; So that I ſee no reaſon to conclude the ſaid <hi>Ioane</hi> to be a Baſtard, until it be proved that ſhe was ſo, by ſome Record, Deed, or good Author who lived in that Age, and eſpecially ſince the ſaid <hi>Hawiſia</hi>'s daughter (if ſhe had one) might very well be old enough in the year 1204. to be married to the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin</hi> Prince of <hi>North-Wales;</hi> But it is not material to the caſe in hand, whether the ſaid <hi>Ioane</hi> was a Baſtard or not, Becauſe all the Gifts you mention in your <hi>Addenda,</hi> were either not gifts <hi>in free-marriage,</hi> or elſe were not given to the ſaid <hi>Lhewellin</hi> with the ſaid <hi>Ioane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to what you ſay in your 7 <hi>Page,</hi> I did in my former Book give you ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Reaſons, why the words of <hi>Glanvil</hi> did not prove what you ſuppoſed they did, and in the 38 and 39 <hi>Pages</hi> of my <hi>Reply</hi> did tell you how you had left
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:51200:17"/>them unanſwered, and did alſo there nform you, that Mr. <hi>Glanvil</hi> did not ſay, That Lands might be given with any woman <hi>in liberum maritagium,</hi> but only <hi>in maritagium;</hi> and yet after all this, you have the confidence again to father upon Mr. <hi>Glanvil</hi> what he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver either meant or ſaid.</p>
            <p>In your 8. <hi>Page,</hi> you ſay I have charged you with <hi>many abſolute untruths and groſs abſurdities, and in ſtead of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt and clear Anſwers to the very point or hinge of the controverſie, did burſt out into extravagant expreſſions in things upon the By, which gives you occaſion to imagine that I think my cauſe declining.</hi> But thoſe, and ſeveral other of your expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, ſeeming to proceed more from paſſion then reaſon, I ſhall at preſent paſs them by, and do not doubt, but I ſhall be able to clear my ſelf, from any thing which you have or can particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly charge me withal; And whereas you pretend that my confidence did ariſe, <hi>becauſe you are tied up by your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to write no more touching</hi> Amicia. I will aſſure you I received no encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement thereby, for I do not take you
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:51200:18"/>to be ſo great a Bug-bear as you ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe your ſelf to be; And if I had rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon your promiſe, I had been much miſtaken, but I did very well know what you meant to do, for (beſides what I heard from others) the ſame day my <hi>Reply</hi> was finiſhed, you did write a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to me, wherein was your pretended new precedent of <hi>Budeford</hi> and <hi>Suttehal,</hi> and before any part of my laſt Book was printed, I received notice from your ſervant by your command, that <hi>you would print ſome precedents as</hi> Addenda <hi>to your former Book,</hi> but it ſeems that reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as alſo another, (as I was informed) of writing an <hi>Anſwer</hi> in a third perſons name, were both laid aſide, and what you did came out as <hi>Addenda</hi> to your la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Book; But how, in ſo doing, you were juſt to your word, I cannot ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, for, what you did write till the end of the 7. <hi>Page,</hi> did all concern <hi>Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia;</hi> and, by the ſame reaſon you did write now, you may write alwayes, and ſay you do ſo <hi>as Addenda only</hi> to your ſaid ſecond Book.</p>
            <p>In your 9 <hi>Page</hi> you again tell me, That I begin my <hi>Reply with an untruth,</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:51200:18"/>becauſe I ſay, that thoſe of our County who are underſtanding perſons will eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcerne from ſome of your Omiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that it was ſomething elſe beſides your great love to truth which occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned you to Aſperſe your deceaſed Grandmother, and you tell me I might have done well to have ſhewed; To which I anſwer, that I will not reflect upon perſons in print, but if any one deſire privately to know what thoſe Omiſſions were, if I cannot give full ſatisfaction of your groſs partiality, let me bear the blame: And, I know no reaſon, ſince you pretended it was your great love to truth which did occaſion you to Write againſt <hi>Amicia,</hi> but that I might in general termes let the World know it was ſomething elſe which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved you ſo to do; and I will appeale to the Reader, whether I did not avoid all offenſive expreſſions in what I ſaid.</p>
            <p>In your 10. <hi>Page,</hi> you are alſo over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>captious; For I having found in your <hi>Hiſtorical Antiquities</hi> two Deeds made by <hi>Randle</hi> de <hi>Gernoniis</hi> father to <hi>Hugh Cyveliok,</hi> (in the time of which <hi>Hugh,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:51200:19"/>Raph Mainwaring</hi> was Juſtice of <hi>Cheſter</hi>) and thoſe two Deeds being directed <hi>Juſticiariis,</hi> although I know of none who can tell the name of any more then one of them; I did therefore, leſt there ſhould be two Juſtices in the time of the ſaid <hi>Raph,</hi> in my firſt Book call him <hi>Chiefe Juſtice,</hi> becauſe he acted alone, but did withal in my ſecond Book acknowledge, that I had not found that there was then any other Juſtice in the time of the ſaid <hi>Raph,</hi> and for this, you tell me I ſhould have been more ingenious, and do ſay, <hi>I do very well know that there was no other Judge of</hi> Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>at that time,</hi> which being a Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, it is impoſſible for me to know; Alſo, as you may ſee in <hi>Monaſticon An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glicanum, Part</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 97 &amp; 226. and in your <hi>Hiſt. Ant. p.</hi> 130. &amp; 131. there was in the time of the ſaid Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times two Juſtices of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times but one; So that there poſſibly might be another Juſtice of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> when the ſaid <hi>Raph</hi> was Judge there: And whereas you give a glance at my vain-glory, by pretending <hi>you are loath to ſay it was ſo:</hi> I deſire to know how I could poſſibly be vain-glorious therein<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:51200:19"/>ſince it was full as honourable for the ſaid <hi>Raph</hi> to be <hi>ſole</hi> Juſtice of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> as to be <hi>Chiefe</hi> Juſtice in caſe there were two.</p>
            <p>In your 11 and 12 <hi>Pages,</hi> you deny that you ſaid that <hi>Geffrey Dutton</hi> was witneſs to his own Deed or Deeds, but to the Deeds of others, and ſay, it was my groſs miſtake in ſaying ſo; But, if any perſons read the 4 and 5 <hi>Pages</hi> of your <hi>Anſwer</hi> to my firſt Book, they may eaſily ſee that you apply the words <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino Galfrido de Dutton</hi> in that Deed of <hi>Tabley</hi> to that <hi>Jeffrey</hi> de <hi>Dutton</hi> who made the ſaid Deed, and they will alſo find you ſaying, <hi>That in ſeveral other Deeds of the ſame perſon</hi> (meaning ſtill the ſame <hi>Geffrey</hi>) <hi>you dare affirm among the</hi> witneſſes ſubſcribed <hi>he hath five times and more the word</hi> Dominus <hi>omitted, for once that we find it prefixed to his name.</hi> Let the Readers therefore (if they can) find out, how you could imagine his name to be at any time amongſt his own Witneſſes, if you did not take him to be a Witneſs to his own Deeds.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:51200:20"/>You alſo in the ſame <hi>Pages</hi> of your <hi>Addenda</hi> ſay, <hi>That if he had been a Knight he would have called himſelf by his Title, Ego</hi> Galfridus <hi>de</hi> Dutton <hi>Miles;</hi> or, <hi>Ego Dominus</hi> Galfridus <hi>de</hi> Dutton <hi>dedi,</hi> &amp;c. But, this is directly contrary to what you did write at the bottom of the 5. <hi>Page</hi> of your ſecond Book; and it is well known, that in very antient times, every one who was a Knight, did not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes give himſelf the Title of <hi>Miles</hi> or <hi>Dominus</hi> in his own Deeds, neither had he alwayes the ſame Title given to him by others, which, if occaſion required, I could make to appear.</p>
            <p>You alſo tell me, that when I ſay <hi>That Dominus</hi> Galfridus <hi>de</hi> Dutton <hi>wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the other</hi> Geffrey Duttons <hi>Deed of</hi> Nether-Tabley <hi>was his Father, <hi>it was my groſs miſtake,</hi> For it was</hi> Geffrey Dutton <hi>of</hi> Chedle. And you alſo ſay, that <hi>there were four</hi> Geffrey Duttons, <hi>two of</hi> Budworth, <hi>Father and Son, and two of</hi> Chedle <hi>Father and Son, much contemporary;</hi> and for the proving of thoſe two of <hi>Budworth</hi> (thoſe of <hi>Chedle</hi> being not there named) you ſend me to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:51200:20"/>your Book of <hi>Antiquities, Page</hi> 226. <hi>there to be informed of what</hi> (you ſay) <hi>you ſee I do not know.</hi> But, if I did not know of thoſe two <hi>Geffrey Duttons,</hi> how could I tell you in the 10. <hi>Page</hi> of my <hi>Reply</hi> that <hi>Adam</hi> de <hi>Dutton</hi> had iſſue Sir <hi>Jeffrey,</hi> who had iſſue <hi>Geffrey</hi> who made the ſaid Deed of <hi>Tabley?</hi> or, How could I ſay that <hi>Geffrey</hi> the Father was a Witneſs to that Deed? and, How doth it yet appear that the <hi>Dominus</hi> Galfri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus <hi>de</hi> Dutton, who was Witneſs to the ſaid Deed of <hi>Tabley</hi> was <hi>Geffrey Dutton</hi> of <hi>Chedle,</hi> and not the other Sir <hi>Geffrey Dutton</hi> of <hi>Budworth?</hi> For, though the year 1238 be the laſt time you ſay you met with him, yet, as appears in your <hi>Hiſt. Antiq. p.</hi> 216. you have not ſeen the Deeds of Sir <hi>George Warburton,</hi> who is his heir-male; therefore the ſaid <hi>Geffrey</hi> might very well live on to be a Witneſs to that Deed. But, whether the ſaid Sir <hi>Geffrey</hi> of <hi>Budworth</hi> the Father was then living or not, one of the <hi>Geffrey Duttons</hi> of <hi>Chedle</hi> was alſo a Knight, as appears in your <hi>Hiſt. Ant. p.</hi> 206. (though you conceal it in your <hi>Addenda</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you would have the Reader to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve there was no Sir <hi>Geffrey Dutton</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:51200:21"/>living when that Deed of <hi>Tabley</hi> was made) which will as well ſerve my turn; for, if Sir <hi>Geffrey</hi> of <hi>Budworth</hi> was then dead, then the <hi>Domino Galfrido de Dutton</hi> is in that Deed to be applied to Sir <hi>Geffrey Dutton</hi> of <hi>Chedle;</hi> And whilſt they were both living, whenſoever you ſind <hi>Domino Galfrido de Dutton</hi> among the witneſſes, it is certainly to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to one of the Knights, and when you find <hi>Galfrido</hi> without <hi>Domino,</hi> it is as certainly meant of ſome <hi>Geffry Dutton</hi> that was no Knight.</p>
            <p>And whereas you object, <hi>p.</hi> 13. <hi>That Sir</hi> Geffrey Dutton <hi>of</hi> Budworth <hi>muſt needs be dead, or elſe</hi> Geffrey <hi>the Son could not have paſſed away thoſe Lands.</hi> That doth not follow, for I have known more then once, not only Sons in the life-times of their Fathers, but alſo Grandchildren, who have been poſſeſſed of Lands in their grandfathers time; And whereas you ſay that <hi>Margaret</hi> was daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but not Daughter and <hi>heir</hi> of <hi>Geffrey Dutton;</hi> I cannot tell how that will appear without the ſight of Sir <hi>George Warburtons</hi> Deeds; Becauſe Sir <hi>Peter Dutton</hi> might be ſon to a <hi>Geffrey Dutton,</hi> and yet be
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:51200:21"/>Brother and heir-mal to <hi>Geffrey</hi> the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Margaret.</hi> But be it how it will, ſhe having the Mannors of <hi>Nether-Tabley, Wethale,</hi> and <hi>Hield,</hi> it can be no groſs one, if it be any miſtake at all.</p>
            <p>In your 14 <hi>Page,</hi> you would willingly heal an expreſſion in your former Book, by confeſſing it was too ſhort; but, to make amends for this, you now overdoe it; and becauſe you would make us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that you formely meant as you now pretend, you ſay, that a little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, you did ſpeak of Knights who uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſtiled themſelves thus—<hi>Ego Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> A. B. <hi>dedi,</hi> &amp;c. or, <hi>Ego Dominus</hi> A. B. <hi>Miles dedi,</hi> &amp;c. But, whoever can find thoſe words in your <hi>Anſwer,</hi> can find out that which I am not able to do.</p>
            <p>In your 16, 17 and 18 <hi>Pages,</hi> you keep a great ſtir about the word <hi>domino,</hi> when it is prefixed to any names in ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and though you were willing in your laſt Book to call Sir <hi>Raph Mainwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,</hi> Sir <hi>Roger Mainwaring,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Mainwaring,</hi> and Sir <hi>William Mainwaring,</hi> all of them Knights, yet now you are
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:51200:22"/>diſſatisfied concerning all but Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Mainwaring,</hi> to whoſe name in a Fine you find the word <hi>Milite</hi> added, and you would willingly inſinuate that the <hi>Dominus Willielmus Mainwaring</hi> was he who was Parſon of <hi>Wernith,</hi> (though without any cauſe as appears by the Deed wherein he is named.) And you ask me, whether I have any Deed of <hi>Raph Mainwaring</hi> Judge of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> with the word <hi>Milite</hi> added, which you well know that I have not, it being much, that I have thoſe Deeds of his which I have, being he was Judge of <hi>Cheſter</hi> ſo long ſince, <hi>viz.</hi> in the time of <hi>Richard</hi> the Firſt; But, I pray you, Why is not the word <hi>Domino,</hi> when prefixed to the name of a Witneſs who was not a Clergy-man, good proof that he was a Knight? (eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially ſince ſome who are likely to be the moſt skilful in thoſe matters, are of opinion that it is.) And why, if it be not good proof, were you lately more complemental then you are now, and did break your old Rule of <hi>Amicus So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates, Amicus Plato,</hi> &amp;c. in calling <hi>Raph, Roger,</hi> and <hi>William Mainwaring</hi> Knights? Or, Why do not you prove the word <hi>domino</hi> prefixed to ſome perſons name,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:51200:22"/>before he was made a Knight? Or, to one who was no Clergy-man, and but an Eſquire, at the time of his death? Or, Why doth not the word <hi>domino</hi> prefixed to each of the names of the aforeſaid <hi>Raph, Roger,</hi> and <hi>William Mainwaring</hi> prove them to be Knights, as well as it doth prove one of the <hi>Geffrey Duttons</hi> of <hi>Budworth,</hi> and one of the <hi>Geffrey Duttons</hi> of <hi>Chedle</hi> to be Knights? For, you confeſs, <hi>Page</hi> 13. of your <hi>Addenda,</hi> that you do not remember any of them writing <hi>Ego Dominus</hi> Galfridus Dutton, <hi>dedi,</hi> &amp;c. And, Why did not you an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Queſtion which I asked of you in the 16. <hi>Page</hi> of my <hi>Reply?</hi> viz. <hi>If the word</hi> Dominus <hi>do only ſignifie</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, <hi>(as you would have it) What is the reaſon, that in ſome Deeds it is only put be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the names of ſome of the witneſſes, and not before the names of others? although thoſe other perſons to whoſe names it is not put, many times are Lords of ſeveral Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, and perſons of very great Eſtate.</hi> And, What is the reaſon that you do not call all the four <hi>Geffrey Duttons</hi> Knights, as well as two of them? ſeeing in the 13 <hi>p.</hi> you ſay, <hi>You have (if you miſtake not) ſeen them all ſometimes ſubſcribed with</hi> Domino
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:51200:23"/>
               <hi>prefixed,</hi> but not <hi>any of them writing himſelf,</hi> Ego Dominus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Or, How comes it to paſs, that neither of the two Knights did ever write ſo, if what you ſay in your 11th <hi>Page</hi> be true? Sure the <hi>Reader</hi> will eaſily perceive, what ſtrange work you yet make with theſe <hi>Geffreys</hi> and their <hi>Deeds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In your 18th <hi>Page</hi> you alſo ſay, <hi>That I faſten upon you another untruth, where I tell you, that you have ſeen the opinion of a Judge under his hand, with Reaſons for the ſame touching</hi> Amicia. But, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this be an untruth or not, let what you formerly ſent me under your own hand determine, where you name the Judge, and alſo take notice that his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were given under his hand; Let me therefore adviſe you for the future to be more cautious what you write. And whereas you alſo ſay, <hi>That your memory is not ſo bad, but you could remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſomething of it or his name;</hi> Let the Reader look in your <hi>Hiſt. Ant. p.</hi> 135. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>and p.</hi> 136. <hi>l.</hi> 43. or ſee your words in the 5 <hi>p. l.</hi> 15. <hi>and</hi> 12. <hi>p. l.</hi> 5. printed with my <hi>Defence</hi> of <hi>Amicia,</hi> and he will there find that you did know the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the ſaid Judge.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:51200:23"/>And whereas you pretend, <hi>It was impoſſible for you to have alleadged to the two Heralds, the tenth part of what you could have done in ſo ſhort a ſpace;</hi> I ſhall leave that to them, they being both yet living, as alſo whether they have found any thing in your former Books con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Amicia,</hi> which they have not heard from you before. And as for your Lawyer of very good note, and good <hi>Antiquary,</hi> you do well in conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Name, But certainly he was very unkind that would not furniſh you with ſome Precedents to make good what he ſaid.</p>
            <p>What you ſay in the 20th <hi>Page,</hi> and ſo on to the middle of the 23 <hi>Page,</hi> ſhews clearly, that you are reſolved not to be convinced; For, when at the firſt I proved out of <hi>Monaſt. Angl. Part</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 267. that <hi>Richard Bacuns</hi> Mother could not be <hi>Hugh Cyveliok's</hi> daughter, becauſe it was <hi>Randle</hi> de <hi>Gernoniis,</hi> not <hi>Randle Blundevil,</hi> whom the ſaid <hi>Richard</hi> called Unckle, in regard there was a <hi>William</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>York,</hi> and one whoſe Name began with an <hi>R.</hi> which was then
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:51200:24"/>Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> both living in the time of the ſaid <hi>Randle</hi> de <hi>Gernoniis:</hi> but that there was no <hi>William</hi> Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>York,</hi> during all the time of <hi>Randle Blundevil,</hi> nor any man Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter</hi> whoſe name began with <hi>R,</hi> after the ſaid <hi>Randle Blundevil</hi> could be old enough to ſeal a Deed, as alſo, becauſe <hi>Bacuns</hi> witneſſes were contemporary with <hi>Randle</hi> de <hi>Gernoniis;</hi> You in the 54 and 55 <hi>Pages</hi> of your <hi>Anſwer,</hi> do not only ſay that you conceive the <hi>Roll</hi> from whence the Deed in <hi>Monaſticon</hi> was written is miſtaken in <hi>Will.</hi> and <hi>R.</hi> (which was a ſtrange Anſwer) but you alſo ſay, <hi>There was no ſuch Archbiſhop of</hi> York <hi>called</hi> William, <hi>nor Biſhop of</hi> Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>whoſe Chriſtian name began with R. both living at one time, either in the time of</hi> Randle Blundevil <hi>or</hi> Randle <hi>de</hi> Gerno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niis <hi>that you can find.</hi> But when you perceived that I had clearly proved by ſeveral Authors, that a <hi>William</hi> was Archbiſhop of <hi>York,</hi> and that <hi>Roger Clin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> was Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter</hi> in the time of <hi>Randle</hi> de <hi>Gernoniis,</hi> ſo that you could no longer deny the ſame; You now in your <hi>Addenda</hi> would willingly avoid the Argument, becauſe the ſaid <hi>William</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:51200:24"/>upon his firſt Election had not the <hi>Pall,</hi> which all that know any thing will eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceive to be a very weak Anſwer; For he was conſecrated Archbiſhop, and had poſſeſſion of the Archbiſhoprick till after the deaths of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, Pope <hi>Celeſtine</hi> the Second, and Pope <hi>Lucius</hi> the Second; And if he was reputed Archbiſhop, he would be called ſo, as well in Deeds as otherwayes: And it is no wonder, ſince he was look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon by many to be the right Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop, and to be wrongfully ſuſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Pope <hi>Engenius,</hi> (as you may ſee in my <hi>Reply, Page</hi> 77. and ſo on to the 87. <hi>Page</hi>) if ſome perſons do name him according to the time of Election, and others according to the time of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration, which doth reconcile thoſe different placings which you mention in your 22 <hi>p.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas you again object, That <hi>Chester</hi> was then within the Province of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> not <hi>York;</hi> I anſwered that in my laſt Book, where I told you that the Archbiſhop was not named upon that accompt, but becauſe ſome of the places mentioned in the ſaid Deed were
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:51200:25"/>within the Province and Dioceſs of <hi>York,</hi> as particularly <hi>Roſington</hi> was, it being within the Weſtriding of <hi>York ſhire;</hi> And if that Deed was not directed to an Archbiſhop of <hi>York,</hi> How came the word <hi>Eboracenſi</hi> there? But if you had foreſeen I would have asked you this queſtion, I doubt not but you would have ſaid, <hi>That the word</hi> Eboracenſi <hi>was miſwrit,</hi> as well as the word <hi>VVill,</hi> and the letter <hi>R.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In your 23, 24, and 25 <hi>Pages,</hi> you are diſingenious, and do not recite my Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument aright; For you pretend it only to lie in this, That <hi>Hugh VVac</hi> and <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Pincerna</hi> (two of the Witneſſes to <hi>Bacuns</hi> Deeds) were alſo Witneſſes to a Deed made <hi>Anno</hi> 1152. which falls in the latter end of the life of <hi>Randle</hi> de <hi>Gernoniis,</hi> whereas vvhoever vvill read the 88 and 89 <hi>Pages</hi> of my <hi>Reply,</hi> vvill find that I named five Witneſſes of <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Bacuns,</hi> viz. <hi>Hugh Wac, Richard Pineerna, VVilliam Colevile, Thurſtan Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſter,</hi> and <hi>VVilliam</hi> the Chaplain, and alſo did inſtance in five Deeds to vvhich <hi>Randle</hi> de <hi>Gernoniis</hi> vvas a party, to each of vvhich, one, tvvo, or three of the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:51200:25"/>ſaid <hi>Bacuns</hi> ſaid witneſſes were alſo wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes; and if you pleaſe you may alſo find a ſixth Deed in <hi>Monaſt. Angl. Part</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 987. <hi>b.</hi> and a ſeventh Deed in <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſt. Angl. Part</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 260. <hi>b.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which you did alleadg concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing two Deeds made at a great diſtance, is nothing like this Caſe; Neither is there any weight in <hi>William Bacun's</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a witneſs to a ſingle Deed of <hi>Randle Blundevils,</hi> for, he might be a young Man when he was witneſs to <hi>Richard Bacuns</hi> Deed, and living to be old might be a witneſs to one of <hi>Randle Blundevils</hi> Deeds, But it is probable he was Son, Grandſon, or other Kinſman of the other <hi>VVilliam Bacun;</hi> But, you deal a little fallaciouſly with your Reader, when you ſay it was but Twenty nine years betwixt the death of <hi>Randle</hi> de <hi>Gernoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is,</hi> and the time that <hi>Randle Blundevil</hi> was Earl; For, though that be true, yet it would be a longer time before <hi>Randle Blundevil</hi> could be old enough to ſeal a Deed, for his Mother was but Twenty four years old when he came to be Earl.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:51200:26"/>VVhat you object, <hi>p.</hi> 26 and 27, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the deed of VVarranty of <hi>Randle</hi> de <hi>Gernoniis,</hi> or concerning <hi>Richard Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuns</hi> being contemporary with <hi>Randle Blundevil,</hi> is ſufficiently anſwered; For, VVhy might not the ſaid Deed of War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranty be loſt, as well as many thouſands of other Deeds are? And that <hi>Richard Bacun</hi> was contemporary with <hi>Randle</hi> de <hi>Gernoniis,</hi> I have abundantly proved. And though in your 27 <hi>Page,</hi> you would have <hi>Bacuns</hi> Mother to be <hi>Hugh Cyveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oks</hi> daughter, yet in the 25 <hi>Page</hi> you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that <hi>it is probable ſhe was a Baſtard of</hi> Randle <hi>de</hi> Meſchines, but finding that to contradict what you afterwards ſaid, you have ſince the Printing thereof blotted it out of thoſe Books which you have diſpoſed of in theſe parts; And, although I do not ſee but that <hi>Bacuns</hi> Mother might be a lawful daughter of the ſaid <hi>Randle</hi> de <hi>Meſchines,</hi> yet I will not further engage in her defence, but paſs by that, and the courſe language which you repeat at the latter end of your Book.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:51200:26"/>I have now done with your <hi>Addenda</hi> but ſince you have ſo abounded in that, particular, I hope you will give me leave to add a word or two to what I have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſaid.</p>
            <p>I have heretofore proved that the aforeſaid <hi>Bertred</hi> was but Twenty four years of age in the year 1181, when her Husband died, by which it appears, that ſhe was born in the year 1157. I do alſo find in the Third Part of Mr. <hi>Dug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dales Monaſticon Anglicanum, p.</hi> 226. that <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> and his Mother <hi>Maude</hi> did give <hi>Stivinghale,</hi> with a Mill next the Park, and ſome other Grounds, to <hi>VVal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Durdent</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter</hi> and his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, to which Deed <hi>Euſtace</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable was witneſs; Now the ſaid Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> being not in a capacity to ſeal a Deed until he was One and twenty years of age, and the ſaid <hi>Euſtace</hi> being ſlain (as appears by your <hi>Hiſt. Ant. p.</hi> 266.) in a Battel againſt the <hi>VVelſh</hi> in the ſaid year 1157. If the ſaid Deed was made immediately before the ſaid <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtace</hi> was ſlain, the ſaid <hi>Hugh</hi> muſt needs be at the leaſt One and twenty years ol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:51200:27"/>then his Wife <hi>Bertred;</hi> But, it is very likely that Deed was made ſome years before, <hi>viz.</hi> immediately upon the death of <hi>Randle</hi> de <hi>Gernoniis,</hi> For the ſaid <hi>Randle</hi> died Excommunicate, and <hi>Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinghale</hi> and thoſe other Lands were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for his Abſolution, and the health of his Soul.</p>
            <p>But, beſides what is here proved, if you look at the latter end of the <hi>VVelſh Hiſtory</hi> put out by Dr. <hi>Powel</hi> 1584, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately before the Table, you will ſee that the 16 line of the 197 page of the ſaid <hi>VVelſh Hiſtory</hi> is miſprinted, and that in the ſaid Page it ſhould have been Printed thus: <hi>About the ſame time</hi> Hugh <hi>ſon to the Earl of</hi> Cheſter, <hi>ſprti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied his Caſtell of</hi> Cymaron, <hi>and wan</hi> Melienyth <hi>to himſelf.</hi> And you may alſo there find, that the time when the ſaid <hi>Hugh</hi> wan <hi>Mclienith</hi> was in the year 1142.</p>
            <p>Now that this <hi>Welſh Hiſtory</hi> is of good credit, I hope you will not deny; For, in the 44 <hi>Page</hi> of your <hi>Hiſtorical Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> you acknowledge, that in theſe <hi>Welſh</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:51200:27"/>matters you chiefly follow the ſame; And Dr. <hi>Powel</hi> in his Epiſtle, as alſo in his Notes on the ſaid Hiſtory, <hi>p.</hi> 206. tells us, That <hi>Caradocus Lhanearuan</hi> is repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and taken of all learned men to be the Author of what is therein written, until the year 1156. And as you may find in <hi>Voſſius</hi> his Book, <hi>de Hiſtoricis Latinis,</hi> p. 389. and in <hi>Iſaackſons Chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie,</hi> p. 323. the ſaid <hi>Caradocus</hi> was li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving when the ſaid <hi>Hugh</hi> wan <hi>Melie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The only Queſtion therefore is, Of what age the ſaid <hi>Hugh</hi> then was? And becauſe that is uncertain, and that I am willing to reckon ſo, as may be moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous to you, I will ſuppoſe him to be then but Twelve years old, which is the ſame age that <hi>Silveſter Giraldus, p.</hi> 203. ſayes Prince <hi>Lhewellin ap Jor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth</hi> was of, when he began to infeſt his Unckles, and is indeed as young, as I have obſerved any to appear in ſuch Martial Affaires. Now, if we ſhould believe that <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> did Marry the ſaid <hi>Berired</hi> ſo ſoon as ſhe was four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years of age, then the ſaid Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:51200:28"/>would happen in the year 1171. at which time, if <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> was born in the year 1130, and was but 12 years old when he was <hi>Melienith,</hi> in the year 1142, yet he would be 41 years of Age when he Married the ſaid <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred.</hi> It cannot therefore be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that ſo great a perſon ſhould continue unmarryed till he was above Fourty yeares old, or that he ſhould Marry to his firſt Wife, one ſo much different from him in yeares; But, when he had Marryed a former Wife, who dyed leaving him only a daughter or daughters, it is no wonder if in his age, he Marryed a young Lady, to the intent he might have Iſſue-male to ſucceed him in ſo great an Eſtate; I hope therefore, though you told me in the 49 <hi>Page</hi> of your <hi>Reply, That you can gather no ſuch quantity of years</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Hugh Cyvelioks</hi> age, <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably to ſuppoſe him to have had a former Wife,</hi> that theſe proofes will ſhew, that there were very many years betwixt them, and that thereupon you will be ſo reaſonable as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve he had a Wife before he Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:51200:28"/>
               <hi>Bertred;</hi> And, if he had a former Wife, there would be no cauſe to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect <hi>Amicia</hi> to be illegitimate, if your pretended Precedents had been ſuch as you did untruly ſuppoſe them to be; with which I will conclude what I have now to ſay, when I have ſubſcribed my ſelf</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Affectionate Coſin and Servant, Thomas Mainwaring.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Baddeley,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Feb.</hi> 13. 1673/4.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
